xavier.bouthillier@umontreal.ca | *bouthilx.github.io | Douthilx | bouthilx

Summary_

I am a fifth-year PhD student in computer science at Mila, Université de Montréal. I am studying under the supervision of Pascal Vincent, specializing in machine learning, specifically deep learning. I am strongly interested in both research and software development.

During my Master's and PhD, I have done research on a wide array of subjects ranging from NLP, computer vision, and optimization to theoretical deep learning. I am now concentrating on studying the methodology for deep learning research, designing methods to improve reproducibility.

Beside research, I have been an important contributor to tools developed at LISA/Mila such as Theano and Pylearn2 and a mentor for students contributing to these projects. I am now the lead developer of the project Orion, a platform for hyper-parameter optimization, supported by the Mila IDT team and for which we are currently signing collaboration agreements with the industry. I am concurrently developing an automation tool called Mahler, which enables large-scale experimentation for improved reproducibility using statistical tests.

Education

Mila, Université de Montréal

PhD in Computer Science, Machine Learning 2014 - 2020 Master in Computer Science, Machine Learning 2013 - 2014 Bachelor in Computer Science 2009 - 2012

Freiburg Albert-Ludwigs Universität (Germany)

Exchange program during Bachelor's degree 2011-2012

CÉGEP Saint-Laurent

Natural Science 2008 - 2009 2005 - 2008 Music, Composition Profile

Experience

Mila, Université de Montréal Montréal, Canada

Research Developer

Oct. 2017 - Present

• Lead developer of Oríon (See description for Oríon in Open Source Projects)

Nuance Communications Montréal, Canada Research Intern Sep. 2016 - Dec. 2016

· Improved the attention mechanism in the paper Hierarchical Attention Networks for Document Classification

Nuance Communications Montréal, Canada

Research Intern

May. 2016 - Aug. 2016

- Developed an algorithm to generate fake examples based on large medical documents.
- Reproduced the paper Hierarchical Attention Networks for Document Classification.
- Implemented a pipeline to convert large medical documents in deep hierarchical structures.

Nuance Communications Montréal, Canada

Research Intern

Sep. 2014 - Jan. 2015

- Applied deep learning models to a classification problem in natural language processing.
- Developed a new convolutional model inspired by n-grams using PyLearn2.

LISA (Mila), Université de Montréal

Montreal, Canada

2010 - 2012

Research Assistant · Learned website development from scratch.

- · Implemented ¡Query plugins.
- · Maintained website and applied modifications on request.

Teaching Experience

IFT6390 Foundations of machine learning, Teaching Assistant, Université de Montréal

Fall 2014

IFT6390 Foundations of machine learning, Teaching Assistant, Université de Montréal

Fall 2013

Publications

JOURNAL ARTICLES

Emonets: Multimodal Deep Learning Approaches for Emotion Recognition in Video

Samira Ebrahimi Kahou, Xavier Bouthillier, Pascal Lamblin, Caglar Gulcehre, Vincent Michalski, Kishore Konda, Sébastien Jean, Pierre Froumenty, Yann Dauphin, Nicolas Boulanger-Lewandowski

Journal on Multimodal User Interfaces 10.2 (2016) pp. 99-111. Springer, 2016

CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

Unreproducible Research is Reproducible

Xavier Bouthillier, César Laurent, Pascal Vincent

International Conference on Machine Learning, 2019

Fast Approximate Natural Gradient Descent in a Kronecker Factored Eigenbasis

Thomas George, César Laurent, Xavier Bouthillier, Nicolas Ballas, Pascal Vincent

Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, 2018

Efficient Exact Gradient Update for Training Deep Networks with Very Large Sparse Targets

Pascal Vincent, Alexandre De Brébisson, Xavier Bouthillier

Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, 2015

Combining Modality Specific Deep Neural Networks for Emotion Recognition in Video

Samira Ebrahimi Kahou, Christopher Pal, Xavier Bouthillier, Pierre Froumenty, Çaglar Gülçehre, Roland Memisevic, Pascal Vincent, Aaron Courville, Yoshua Bengio, Raul Chandias Ferrari

Proceedings of the 15th ACM on International conference on multimodal interaction, 2013

WORKSHOPS

Improving Reproducibility of Benchmarks

Xavier Bouthillier

CiML Workshop at Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, 2019

An Evaluation of Fisher Approximations Beyond Kronecker Factorization

César Laurent, Thomas George, Xavier Bouthillier, Nicolas Ballas, Pascal Vincent

Workshop at International Conference on Learning Representations, 2018

Oríon: Experiment Version Control for Efficient Hyperparameter Optimization

Christos Tsirigotis, Xavier Bouthillier, François Corneau-Tremblay, Peter Henderson, Reyhane Askari, Samuel Lavoie-Marchildon, Tristan Deleu, Dendi Suhubdy, Michael Noukhovitch, Frédéric Bastien

AutoML Workshop at the International Conference on Machine Learning, 2018

REPORTS

Theano: A Python Framework for Fast Computation of Mathematical Expressions

The Theano Development Team, Rami Al-Rfou, Guillaume Alain, Amjad Almahairi, Christof Angermueller, Dzmitry Bahdanau, Nicolas Ballas, Frédéric Bastien, Justin Bayer, Anatoly Belikov, ...

arXiv preprint arXiv:1605.02688 (2016). 2016

Exact Gradient Updates in Time Independent of Output Size for the Spherical Loss Family

Pascal Vincent, Alexandre Brébisson, Xavier Bouthillier

arXiv preprint arXiv:1606.08061 (2016). 2016

Dropout as Data Augmentation

Xavier Bouthillier, Kishore Konda, Pascal Vincent, Roland Memisevic

arXiv preprint arXiv:1506.08700 (2015). 2015

Open Source Projects

Orion (github.com/Epistimio/orion)

Oríon is an open-source framework developed at Mila for distributed black-box optimization.

2017-Present

- Lead project directions and main goals
- Design architecture of the framework
- · Recruit and interview potential candidates for Mila IDT team
- · Mentor interns

Lead developer

- Design governance rules
- Provide support to users
- · Give presentations and tutorials
- · Write extensive documentation in reStructuredText
- Setup and maintain CI with Travis and codecov
- · Implemented an experiment version control system

Mahler (bouthilx.github.io/projects/2-mahler)

Developer - Prototype stage

2019-Present Mahler is a framework to provide more control over workflow, better resiliency and better automation in HPC

- Implemented an automated remote installations using Fabrik for multi-cluster setups.
- Implemented a singularity-based workflow to easily deploy experiments on different clusters.
- Implemented a Dispatcher that monitors GPU usage and oversubscribe them with additional workers if possible.
- · Implemented a dashboard using Dash to provide visualization and control over the pool of workers and registered tasks.

Kleio (bouthilx.github.io/projects/4-kleio)

Developer - Prototype stage

Kleió is an experiment manager that provides full traceability.

2018-Present

- Implemented a new data architecture based on the concept of events sourcing.
- Implemented remote commands (cat, tail, head, ...) for logs of experiments.

Theano (github.com/Theano/Theano)

Supervisor

2015-2017

Theano is a Python library that allows you to define, optimize, and evaluate mathematical expressions efficiently

· Mentored students contributing for the Common-Code-Workflow

Presentations

4 Dec 2019	Unreproducible Research is Reproducible tinyurl.com/w6kmn2d	CHAI, Berkeley, USA
28 Nov 2019	Oríon: A Framework for Distributed Hyperparameter Optimisation tinyurl.com/t4ubtb4	Mila, Montreal, Canada
21 Nov 2019	Reproducibility in machine learning, or why benchmarks are lotteries	Mila, Montreal, Canada
21 Nov 2019	tinyurl.com/u54a7o6 Orion: A Framework for Distributed Hyperparameter Optimisation tinyurl.com/scxq63b	Mila, Montreal, Canada
	Unreproducible Research is Reproducible tinyurl.com/rkgp55k	Mila, Montreal, Canada
31 Jul 2019	Reproducibility in AI tinyurl.com/roue8js	Stradigi AI, Montreal, Canada
13 Jun 2019	Unreproducible Research is Reproducible tinyurl.com/w52vjsy	ICML, Long Beach, USA
10 Apr 2019	Introduction à l'intelligence artificielle	UdeM, Montreal, Canada
	Presentation to children in a special educational program for intellectual giftedness	
14 Nov 2018	Intelligence artificielle: Une fabrique à outils tinyurl.com/yx6thyjd	CPI, Montreal, Canada
12 Nov 2018	Introduction à l'intelligence artificielle	Collège Montmorency,
	Presentation to high school students for the Forum des jeunes en science	Laval, Canada
30 Aug 2018	Tutorial on Oríon tinyurl.com/u4pjkjy	Mila, Montreal, Canada
14 Jul 2018	Oríon: Experiment Version Control for Efficient Hyperparameter Optimization	ICML, Stockholm, Sweden
26 Apr 2014	Introduction au langage de programmation Python	Google, Montreal, Canada

Extracurricular Activity _____

Reviewer

NeurIPS, ICML, ICLR, Neural Computation, AutoML Workshop, Reproducibility Challenge

2015 - Present

Workshop Organizer

Retrospectives Workshop Dec. 2019

Streaming Designer and Organizer

Mila, Université de Montréal Mar. 2018 - Oct. 2018

- Designed from scratch the setup, procedure and guidelines for recording and streaming at Mila.
- Trained dozen of volunteers to record and stream about a dozen different reading groups at Mila.
- Recorded and streamed weekly talks and PhD defenses.
- * Received a price of 6000\$ to reward the quality and importance of the initiative and the work done.

DECEMBER 11, 2019